<descriptions>
  <variable name="abort_unmodified" type="quad-option">
    <init>yes</init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      If set to <val>yes</val>, composition will automatically abort after
      editing the message body if no changes are made to the file (this
      check only happens after the <em>first</em> edit of the file).
      When set to <val>no</val>, composition will never be aborted.
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="allow_8bit" type="boolean">
    <init>yes</init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      Controls whether 8-bit data is converted to 7-bit using either
      <enc>quoted-printable</enc> or <enc>base64</enc> encoding when
      sending mail.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="assumed_charset" type="string">
    <init>us-ascii</init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      This variable is a colon-separated list of character encoding
      schemes for messages without character encoding indication.
      Header field values and message body content without character encoding
      indication would be assumed that they are written in one of this list.
      </p>
      <p>
      By default, all the header fields and message body without any charset
      indication are assumed to be in <enc>us-ascii</enc>.
      </p>
      <p>
      For example, Japanese users might prefer this:
      <pre>
      set assumed_charset="iso-2022-jp:euc-jp:shift_jis:utf-8"
      </pre>
      </p>
      <p>
      However, only the first content is valid for the message body.
      This variable is valid only if <varref>strict_mime</varref> is <val>unset</val>.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="debug_level" type="number">
    <init>0</init>
    <sig>yes</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      This variable specifies the current debug level and, currently,
      must be in the range 0 to 5. The value 0 has the special meaning
      that no debug is to be generated. From a value of 1 to 5 the
      amount of debug info written increases drastically.
      </p>
      <p>
      Debug files will be written to the home directory by default and to
      the current if the home directory cannot be determinded.
      </p>
      <p>
      Debug files will have a name of the following format:
      <tt>.[scope].[pid].[id].log</tt>, whereby:
      <ul>
        <li><tt>[scope]</tt> is an identifier for where the output came.
          One file will be created for <tt>libmuttng</tt> and one for the
          tool using it such as <man>muttng</man> or <man>muttgn-conf</man>
          </li>
        <li><tt>[pid]</tt> is the current process ID</li>
        <li><tt>[id]</tt> is the debug sequence number. For the first debug
          file of the current session it'll be 1 and increased for
          subsequent enabling/disabling of debug output via this variable</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="folder" type="url">
    <init>file:///tmp/Mail</init>
    <sig>yes</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      Specifies the default location of your mailboxes.
      </p>
      <p>
      A <tt>+</tt> or <tt>=</tt> at the beginning of a pathname will be expanded
      to the value of this variable.
      </p>
      <p>
      Note that if you change this variable from
      the default value you need to make sure that the assignment occurs
      <em>before</em> you use <tt>+</tt> or <tt>=</tt> for any other variables
      since expansion takes place during the <cmdref>set</cmdref> command.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="mbox" type="url">
    <init>file:///tmp/mbox</init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      This specifies the folder into which read mail in your
      <varref>spoolfile</varref> folder will be appended.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="postponed" type="url">
    <init>file:///tmp/postponed</init>
    <sig>yes</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      Mutt-ng allows you to indefinitely ``<funcref>postpone</funcref> sending a message'' which
      you are editing. When you choose to postpone a message, Mutt-ng saves it
      in the mailbox specified by this variable.
      </p>
      <p>
      Also see the <varref>postpone</varref> variable.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="record" type="url">
    <init></init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      This specifies the file into which your outgoing messages should be
      appended. (This is meant as the primary method for saving a copy of
      your messages, but another way to do this is using the <cmdref>my_hdr</cmdref>
      command to create a <hdr>Bcc:</hdr> header field with your email address in it.)
      </p>
      <p>
      The value of <varref>record</varref> is overridden by the <varref>force_name</varref>
      and <varref>save_name</varref> variables, and the <cmdref>fcc-hook</cmdref> command.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
  <variable name="umask" type="number">
    <init>0077</init>
    <sig>no</sig>
    <descr>
      <p>
      This variable specifies the <em>octal</em> permissions for
      <man sect="2">umask</man>. See <man>chmod</man> for possible
      value.
      </p>
    </descr>
  </variable>
</descriptions>
