<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<mainpage>
  
  <head>
    <title>The Mutt Next Generation E-Mail Client</title>
  </head>

  <content>

    <chapter id="introduction"> <!--{{{-->
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>
        <em>Mutt next generation</em> (short <em>mutt-ng</em>) is a fork of the
        well-known email client <em>mutt</em> with the goal to both incorporate
        all the patches that are floating around in the web, and to fix all the
        other little annoyances of mutt.
      </p>

      <p>
        As we early ran intro problems due to the quality of the original source
        and its documentation, we're currently rewriting some parts from scratch.
        Thus, there's not really something to run and test yet.
      </p>

      <p>
        As one of the things we try to improve is documentation in general,
        the documentation is put here and updated frequently.
      </p>

    </chapter>
    <!--}}}-->

    <chapter id="docs"> <!--{{{-->
      <title>Documentation</title>

      <section id="docs-users"> <!--{{{-->
        <title>For users</title>

        <p>
          As the manual will be re-worked completely, too, it is
          still far from being complete. The current manual is
          available in the following languages:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li><web>http://mutt-ng.berlios.de/rewrite/manual/en/</web>: English</li>
          <li><web>http://mutt-ng.berlios.de/rewrite/manual/de_DE/</web>: German</li>
        </ul>

      </section>
      <!--}}}-->

      <section id="docs-devel"> <!--{{{-->
        <title>For developers</title>

        <p>
          The whole source code will be fully documented via
          doxygen (see <web>http://www.doxygen.org/</web>.)
        </p>

        <p>
          It's only available in English:
          <web>http://mutt-ng.berlios.de/rewrite/doxygen/</web>
        </p>

      </section>
      <!--}}}-->

    </chapter>
    <!--}}}-->
  
    <chapter id="download"> <!--{{{-->
      <title>Download</title>

      <p>
        The rewritten source is not yet available as a compressed
        archived but only via subversion. To checkout a working
        copy (assuming subversion is installed), run:
      </p>

      <pre>
$ svn checkout http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/mutt-ng/branches/muttng-rewrite</pre>

    </chapter>
    <!--}}}-->

    <chapter id="feedback"> <!--{{{-->
      <title>Feedback</title>

      <p>
        As the rewrite is in an early stage, please do <em>not</em>
        open bug reports or feature request at our BerliOS.
      </p>

      <p>
        Instead, please contact us via the developer's mailing list:
        <email>mutt-ng-devel@lists.berlios.de</email> only.
      </p>

    </chapter>
    <!--}}}-->

    <chapter id="feeds"> <!--{{{-->
      <title>Newsfeeds</title>

      <p>
        The following newsfeeds or similar sources of information
        can be used to stay up-to-date with the progress of the rewrite:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>this page, of course ;-)</li>
        <li>the development blog found at:
          <web>http://mutt-ng.supersized.org/</web></li>
        <li>the commit messages for the rewrite branch:
          <web>http://user.cs.tu-berlin.de/~pdmef/muttng.cgi?c=muttng-rewrite</web>
          (which also lists several newsfeeds such as RSS, Atom and MBOX)</li>
      </ul>

    </chapter>
    <!--}}}-->

  </content>

</mainpage>
