<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="introduction-overview"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <p>
      <b>Mutt-ng</b> is a small but very
      powerful text-based MIME mail client.  Mutt-ng is highly
      configurable, and is well suited to the mail power user with
      advanced features like key bindings, keyboard macros, mail
      threading, regular expression searches and a powerful pattern
      matching language for selecting groups of messages to perform
      various of types of actions with.
    </p>

    <p>
      The project started off with the mutt code base and got extended with
      more usefull features written on our own as well as patches
      which were already available for mutt. However, by the time we more and
      more ran into the problem that we found the code (mostly) too complex,
      not well enough documented and hardly maintainable any longer when it came to
      tracking down underlying problems of bug reports we received. As the
      consequence, we started to redesign and rewrite everything from scratch.
    </p>

    <p>
      For the rewrite, the main design objectives are:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li><em>Logic separation of funtionality.</em> It turned out that there
        were too few abstraction layers in general but special treatment in just too
        many places. Also it seemed that the main design wasn't questioned at all
        but just got extended by more conditional parts in-place instead of
        migrating to better abstraction models. For the rewrite, we thus use the following
        layer model described later in detail: a <em>core</em> part
        containing very low level but not mail-related functionality, a
        <em>libmuttng</em> library with all mail-related logic and a
        <em>muttng</em> part with user interfaces just using the two lower layers
        as needed. Within each, we separate features and functionality as much
        as possible to move to a more modular system.</li>
      <li><em>Documentation.</em> For developers there virtually wasn't any documentation
        about the design decissions made, the general interaction between different
        parts nor which parts there were. The user-manual was good by means of
        quantity but not quality. For the rewrite, we provide much better documentation
        for users and for developers in as many languages as we find translators for.
        The manual will be completely rewritten, that is, better structured, better
        examples and more accessible for users new to mutt-ng. For developers there's
        better documentation, too. Functions are not only documented, within the different
        layers they're also grouped by their purpose including reasoning for
        the grouping structure. The developer's guide contains plenty documentation
        and ready-to-use examples which are included from compileable source code
        (no copy'n'paste is required, examples are verified automatically to compile
        and work.)</li>
      <li><em>Quality ensurance.</em> As the <em>libmuttng</em> as well as the
        <em>muttng</em> layer is written in C++, there're so-called unit tests which
        are run automatically to see if a certain part works. This greatly improves
        maintainability of the code base not only during the rewrite process but also
        when a redesign is required in the future (as this will certainly be the case, we
        already prepare for it.)</li>
    </ul>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->

  <section id="introduction-homepage"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Mutt-ng Home Page</title>
    
    <p>
      The official hompepage of mutt-ng is: <web>http://www.muttng.org/</web>
    </p>
    
    <p>
      While the rewrite is maintained in a branch, the
      homepage for it is: <web>http://www.muttng.org/rewrite/</web>.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-mailinglists"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Mailing Lists</title>
    
    <p>
      The following mailing lists are available:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <email>mutt-ng-users@lists.berlios.de</email>: This is
        where the mutt-ng user support happens.</li>
      <li>
        <email>mutt-ng-devel@lists.berlios.de</email>: The
        development mailing list for mutt-ng</li>
    </ul>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-distrib-sites"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Software Distribution Sites</title>
    
    <p>
      So far, there are no official releases of Mutt-ng, but you can
      download daily snapshots from <web>http://mutt-ng.berlios.de/snapshots/</web>
      for the ``old'' version.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The code of the rewrite branch is currently only available via
      subversion:
    </p>

    <pre>
$ svn checkout http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/mutt-ng/branches/muttng-rewrite</pre>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-irc"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>IRC</title>
    
    <p>
      Visit channel <tt>#muttng</tt> on <tt>irc.freenode.net</tt>
      (see <web>http://www.freenode.net/</web>) to chat with other people
      interested in Mutt-ng.  
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-weblog"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Weblog</title>
    
    <p>
      If you want to read fresh news about the latest development in
      Mutt-ng, and get informed about stuff like interesting,
      Mutt-ng-related articles and packages for your favorite
      distribution, you can read and/or subscribe to our development
      weblog at <web>http://mutt-ng.supersized.org/</web>.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-copyright"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Copyright</title>
    
    <p>
      Mutt is Copyright (C) 1996-2000 Michael R. Elkins
      <email>me@cs.hmc.edu</email> and others.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
      it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
      the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
      (at your option) any later version.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
      GNU General Public License for more details.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
      along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->

</chapter>
