<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="introduction-overview"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <p>
      <b>Mutt-ng</b> is a small but very
      powerful text-based MIME mail client.  Mutt-ng is highly
      configurable, and is well suited to the mail power user with
      advanced features like key bindings, keyboard macros, mail
      threading, regular expression searches and a powerful pattern
      matching language for selecting groups of messages.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This documentation additionally contains documentation to
      <b>Mutt-NG</b>, a fork from Mutt
      with the goal to fix all the little annoyances of Mutt, to
      integrate all the Mutt patches that are floating around in the
      web, and to add other new features. Features specific to Mutt-ng
      will be discussed in an extra section. Don't be confused when
      most of the documentation talk about Mutt and not Mutt-ng,
      Mutt-ng contains all Mutt features, plus many more.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->

  <section id="introduction-homepage"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Mutt-ng Home Page</title>
    
    <p>
      The official hompepage of mutt-ng is: <web>http://www.muttng.org/</web>
    </p>
    
    <p>
      While the rewrite is maintained in a branch, the
      homepage for it is: <web>http://www.muttng.org/rewrite/</web>.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-mailinglists"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Mailing Lists</title>
    
    <p>
      The following mailing lists are available:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <email>mutt-ng-users@lists.berlios.de</email>: This is
        where the mutt-ng user support happens.</li>
      <li>
        <email>mutt-ng-devel@lists.berlios.de</email>: The
        development mailing list for mutt-ng</li>
    </ul>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-distrib-sites"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Software Distribution Sites</title>
    
    <p>
      So far, there are no official releases of Mutt-ng, but you can
      download daily snapshots from <web>http://mutt-ng.berlios.de/snapshots/</web>
      for the ``old'' version.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The code of the rewrite branch is currently only available via
      subversion:
    </p>

    <pre>
$ svn checkout http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/mutt-ng/branches/muttng-rewrite</pre>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-irc"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>IRC</title>
    
    <p>
      Visit channel <tt>#muttng</tt> on <tt>irc.freenode.net</tt>
      (see <web>http://www.freenode.net/</web>) to chat with other people
      interested in Mutt-ng.  
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-weblog"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Weblog</title>
    
    <p>
      If you want to read fresh news about the latest development in
      Mutt-ng, and get informed about stuff like interesting,
      Mutt-ng-related articles and packages for your favorite
      distribution, you can read and/or subscribe to our development
      weblog at <web>http://mutt-ng.supersized.org/</web>.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->
  
  <section id="introduction-copyright"> <!--{{{-->
    <title>Copyright</title>
    
    <p>
      Mutt is Copyright (C) 1996-2000 Michael R. Elkins
      <email>me@cs.hmc.edu</email> and others.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
      it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
      the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
      (at your option) any later version.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
      GNU General Public License for more details.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
      along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
    </p>
    
  </section>
  <!--}}}-->

</chapter>
